<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<data>
   <event start=" Jan 01 1657 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="George Fox writes letter of caution regarding slavery"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
George Fox wrote a letter of caution "To Friends Beyond Sea, that Have Blacks and Indian Slaves," which expounded the idea of the equality of men in the eyes of God.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1671 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="’Gospel Family-Order’"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
George Fox urged Quaker masters in Barbados to limit their slaves’ terms and to educate them. Fox's statement to Barbadian slaves published in London in Gospel Family-Order, being a short discourse concerning the ordering of families, both whites, blacks and indians in 1676.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1676 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Quaker William Edmundson speaks out against slavery"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
William Edmundson issued an indictment of slavery from Newport , RI "…his courageous decision, announced in slave-trading Newport, gives him first place in the great succession of antislavery apostles." </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1680 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Barbados forbids Friends' Meetings"
 isDuration="false"
link="http://triptych.brynmawr.edu/u?/HC_QuakSlav,3660">
Barbados forbade Friends to hold religious meetings of any kind when they ignored a law against bringing Negroes to meeting, causing a swift decline of Quakerism on the island.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1682 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="William Penn's ‘Articles, Settlement, and Offices’"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
William Penn in his "The Articles, Settlement, and Offices of the Free Society of Traders", 1682, stated that blacks who were imported by the company as servants should be released after fourteen years, provided that "they would thereafter pay the Society two-thirds of what they are capable of producing on such a parcel of land as shall be allotted to them". His plans were not followed by the settlers.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1688 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Germantown Protest"
 isDuration="false"
link="http://triptych.brynmawr.edu/u?/HC_QuakSlav,8">
Germantown Protest Against Slavery.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1693 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="’An Exhortation and Caution to Friends’"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
George Keith published An Exhortation and Caution to Friends Concerning Buying or Keeping of Negroes. This was the first American anti-slavery tract.  It made the point that slaves were prizes taken by violence and this was against the testimony of Friends.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1696 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Philadelphia Yearly Meeting addresses the slave trade"
 isDuration="false"
link="http://triptych.brynmawr.edu/u?/HC_QuakSlav,5839">
William Sotheby and Cadwalader Morgan demanded a ban on slave ownership and importation to the Philadelphia Yearly Meeting. The Yearly Meeting responded by urging slaves be taught the principles of Christian religion and morality and assumed an antislavery stance for the first time. "It is the advice of this meeting that Friends be careful not to encourage the bringing in of any more Negroes."  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1698 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Robert Pyle proposes compensating ex-slaves"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
In addition to suggesting that quarterly meeting should take responsibility for liberating their members' slaves Pyle suggested that meetings should require a settlement between Friends and their ex-slaves to compensate the Negroes for their labor while they had been in bondage.   </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1700 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Philadelphia Quakers open religious meetings for Negroes"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Philadelphia Monthly Meeting, upon the urging of Wm. Penn, instituted religious meetings for Negroes, and encouraged Quakers to send their slaves.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1701 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="New York Friends bring slaves to religious meetings"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
New York Yearly Meeting instructed its members to bring their "children and servants" (slaves) to meeting.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1712 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="William Southeby petitions the Pennsylvania Assembly"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
William Southeby petitioned the Pennsylvania Assembly for the emancipation of all slaves.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1715 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="’The American Defense of the Christian Golden Rule’"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
John Hepburn publishes The American Defense of the Christian Golden Rule and advocates colonization as the logical sequel to emancipation. </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1716 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Rhode Island Quarterly Meeting considers slavery"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Rhode Island Quarterly Meeting received a question from Dartmouth Monthly Meeting if it was "agreeable to Truth to purchase slaves and keep them term of life." The Quarterly Meeting polled its Monthly Meetings, received various responses and decided to wait and see what other Friends did on the question.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1717 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="John Farmer's ‘Epistle concerning Negroes’" 
 isDuration="false"
link="">
John Farmer writes "Epistle concerning Negroes" and presents it at Rhode Island Yearly Meeting. He is advised to "forbear publishing any paper here presented until Friends be further satisfied." Farmer refused and was disowned.    </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1718 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="William Southeby publishes antislavery tract"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
William Southeby, Philadelphia Friend who had worked consistently against slavery, published a paper denouncing slaveholding without the approval of Friends.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1718 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="New York Quakers decide slave-holding is ‘not right’"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
New York Yearly Meeting recorded in its minutes that the matter of "selling and keeping Negroes, men or women slaves, for term of life hath been tenderly spoke to in much love and condescension for the Truth's sake… and the practice was not right.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1718 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="William Burling writes antislavery tract"
 isDuration="false"
link="http://triptych.brynmawr.edu/u?/HC_QuakSlav,6746">
William Burling, New York Yearly Meeting, writes an anti-slavery tract that was later published by Benjamin Lay.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1719 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Philadelphia Yearly Meeting prohibits African slave-trade"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Philadelphia Yearly Meeting’s Book of Discipline prohibits the importation of blacks and the buying or selling of Indian slaves.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1722 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Virginia Yearly Meeting urges kind treatment of slaves"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Virginia Yearly Meeting warned its members against engaging in slave trading as a business and urged them to treat their Negroes kindly.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1727 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="London Yearly Meeting censors slave trade"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
London Yearly Meeting’s epistle reported that the practice of slave trade was censored by the meeting. and that English Friends ruled against the "importation of Negroes from their native country and relations. "  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1729 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Ralph Sandiford publicly criticizes slaveholding Friends"
 isDuration="false"
link="http://triptych.brynmawr.edu/u?/HC_QuakSlav,562">
Ralph Sandiford, Chester Monthly Meeting, was disowned by the yearly meeting for writing a pamphlet that attacked Friends for slave holding, A brief examination of the practice of the time.  It was printed by Benjamin Franklin, although he did not add his name to the title page.  This book reopened the slavery controversy in Philadelphia.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1730 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Philadelphia Yearly Meeting admonishes purchasing slaves"
 isDuration="false"
link="http://triptych.brynmawr.edu/u?/HC_QuakSlav,933">
Chester Monthly Meeting inquired of the Philadelphia Yearly Meeting "Inasmuch as we are restricted by a rule of discipline from being concerned in fetching or importing Negro slaves from their own country, [we wonder] whether it is not as reasonable we should be restricted from buying of them when imported." After conferring with Quarterly Meetings, Philadelphia Yearly Meeting agreed that Friends should be very cautious of purchasing slaves and that meetings should admonish Friends who engaged in the practice.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1733 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="’A Testimony Against that Antichristian Practice’"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Elihu Coleman, Nantucket, published A Testimony Against that Antichristian Practice of Making Slaves of Men. Nantucket and Newport Quarterly Meetings approved it.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1734 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Thomas Chalkley injured in Barbados."
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Thomas Chalkley, Philadelphia Friend, suffered bits of buckshot in Barbados for trying to dissuade the planters from treating their Negroes with tyranny and cruelty.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1737 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Benjamin Lay publishes ‘All slave-keepers’"
 isDuration="false"
link="http://triptych.brynmawr.edu/u?/HC_QuakSlav,6742">
Benjamin Lay publishes All slave-keepers that keep the innocent in bondage, apostates pretending to lay claim to the pure and holy Christian religion. Franklin printed this book but kept his name off the title page.  PYM repudiated the book. Lay was disowned in 1737. Lay demonstrated against slavery at the PYM (bladder of blood) in 1738.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1740 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Virginia Yearly Meeting warns against patrolling for runaways"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Virginia Yearly Meeting decided that Quakers should not serve on the patrols that kept the slaves from running about at night.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1741 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="John Bell's ‘An epistle to Friends’"
 isDuration="false"
link="http://triptych.brynmawr.edu/u?/SC_Broad,128">
John Bell, an English Friend, publishes , An epistle to Friends in Maryland, Barbadoes, and the other colonies, and islands in the West-Indies, where any Friends are . This was particularly noted in New England.  New England Yearly Meeting recommends Bell's Epistle to all its members  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1743 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Philadelphia Yearly Meeting adds query regarding domestic slave trade"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
A query on slave trading was added to Philadelphia Yearly Meeting Discipline.  </event> 
  <event start=" Jan 01 1744 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="New England Yearly Meeting warns against buying slaves"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
In 1743, Rhode Island Quarterly Meeting reported that "the practice of keeping slaves is a matter of uneasiness to many concerned Friends." In 1744, New England Yearly Meeting strengthened its 1717 advice against Friends' importing slaves from the West Indies by including a warning against buying Negroes imported by non-Quaker traders.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1754 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="’Some Considerations on the Keeping of Negroes’"
 isDuration="false"
link="http://triptych.brynmawr.edu/u?/HC_QuakSlav,497">
John Woolman's "Some Considerations on the Keeping of Negroes" published with the approval of Philadelphia Yearly Meeting. Philadelphia Yearly Meeting pays for its publication and supports it distribution in America and England.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1754 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Philadelphia Yearly Meeting publishes antislavery epistle"
 isDuration="false"
link="http://triptych.brynmawr.edu/u?/HC_QuakSlav,1544">
Philadelphia Yearly Meeting published an epistle against slavery that was largely composed by Woolman.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1754 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Seven Years' War begins"
 isDuration="false"
link="http://triptych.brynmawr.edu/u?/HC_QuakSlav,9914">
The conflict of the Seven Years' War causes the Quakers to withdraw from the provincial assembly, leaving the Society energy to consider the question of slavery.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1755 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Philadelphia Yearly Meeting admonishes buying slaves"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Philadelphia Yearly Meeting ordered that Friends who either imported slaves or purchased them locally should be admonished.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1756 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Philadelphia Friends hold religious meetings for Negroes"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Philadelphia Monthly Meeting held quarterly meetings of worship for blacks continuously.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1757 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="John Woolman visits slaveholding Quakers"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
John Woolman visits families of slaveholding Quakers in Maryland, Virginia and North Carolina.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1757 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Virginia Yearly Meeting  adopts moderate antislavery query"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Virginia Yearly Meeting adopted the Philadelphia Queries of 1743 for their own use but modified the one on slave dealing to permit buying slaves for one's own use if no further active participation in the slave trade were involved.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1758 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Philadelphia Quakers appoint a Committee on Negroes"
 isDuration="false"
link="http://triptych.brynmawr.edu/u?/HC_QuakSlav,8865">
Philadelphia Quarterly Meeting appointed a Committee on Negroes, which resolved that the Society should take any step to stop the increase in buying, selling and keeping slaves, and urged the Yearly Meeting to strengthen the minute of 1755.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1758 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Philadelphia Yearly Meeting pressures slaveholding Friends"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Philadelphia Yearly Meeting bans buying and selling slaves, denouncing slavery unequivocally and urged Friends to manumit their blacks. Friends who did not comply were removed from positions of leadership and authority, but not disowned. A visitation committee was formed to treat with Friends who were slaveholders. John Woolman, John Sykes, John Scarborough, John Churchman and Daniel Stanton volunteered for PYM to visit slave owners in order to convince them to give up their slaves. The men reported on their progress at each Yearly Meeting for four years.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1759 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="’Observations on the inslaving, importing and purchasing of negroes’"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Anthony Benezet published Observations on the inslaving, importing and purchasing of negroes: With some advice thereon extracted form [sic] the Yearly Meeting Epistle of London for the present year, Germantown : Printed by Christopher Sower, 1759.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1759 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Baltimore Yearly Meeting prohibits buying slaves"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Maryland Yearly Meeting adopted a new Discipline that placed a prohibition on buying slaves. The next year the rule was repealed, but reinstated at the yearly meeting of 1761  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1761 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="London Yearly Meeting disowns Friends for buying or selling slaves"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
London Yearly Meeting made disownment the penalty for any English Friend who engaged in the slave trade.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1761 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Pennsylvania legislature imposes import duty on slaves"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
A Quaker petition made to the Pennsylvania legislature brought a 10 pound import duty on slaves.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1762 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="’A short account of that part of Africa’"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Anthony Benezet published A short account of that part of Africa, inhabited by the negroes…, Philadelphia, 1762.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1762 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="’Considerations on Keeping Negroes’ (Part II)"
 isDuration="false"
link="http://triptych.brynmawr.edu/u?/HC_QuakSlav,497">
John Woolman published Some Considerations on the keeping of Negroes, Philadelphia : Franklin and Hall, 1762. He paid for the publication himself so it could be more accessible to the public in bookstores.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1762 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="New York Yearly Meeting discourages purchasing Negroes"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
New York Yearly Meeting discourages the further purchasing of Negroes in their revised Discipline.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1762 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Baltimore Yearly Meeting disowns Friends for buying or selling slaves"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Maryland Yearly Meeting made buying and selling Negroes without the consent of a quarterly or monthly meeting a disownable offence.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1763 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Philadelphia Yearly Meeting enforces antislavery discipline"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
The Philadelphia Yearly Meeting appointed a group of 25 men and women to visit all quarterly and monthly meetings assess their adherence to the discipline against owning slaves.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1766 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="’A caution and warning to Great Britain and her colonies’"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Anthony Benezet published A caution and warning to Great Britain and her colonies, in a short representation of the calamitous state of the enslaved Negroes in the British dominions, Philadelphia : H. Miller, 1766.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1768 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Baltimore Yearly Meeting removes slaveholders from leadership"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Maryland Yearly Meeting decided to unconditionally disown members for buying or selling a Negro and removed slaveholding Friends from leadership positions.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1770 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="New England Yearly Meeting forbids slaveholding"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
New England Yearly Meeting forbids slaveholding  A new query was added against transferring slaves in any manner except to free them.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1770 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Africans’ School"
 isDuration="false"
link="http://triptych.brynmawr.edu/u?/HC_QuakSlav,9847">
Anthony Benezet convinced Philadelphia Monthly Meeting to open an “Africans’ School.”  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1771 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="New York Yearly Meeting appoints committee to labor with slaveholders"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
New York Yearly Meeting appointed a committee to labor with slaveholders.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1771 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Maryland assembly imposes import duty on slaves"
 isDuration="false"
link="http://triptych.brynmawr.edu/u?/HC_QuakSlav,493">
A committee of Friends petitioned the Maryland Assembly for a heavy import duty on slaves and secured a tax of 9 pounds.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1772 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="North Carolina Yearly Meeting forbids buying Negroes"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
North Carolina Yearly Meeting insisted that its members should buy no more Negroes except for reasons approved by their Monthly Meeting, such as preventing the breaking up of slave families.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1772 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Slavery ends in Great Britain"
 isDuration="false"
link="http://triptych.brynmawr.edu/u?/HC_QuakSlav,7460">
Slavery ends in Great Britain.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1773 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Moses Brown liberates his slaves and becomes a Quaker"
 isDuration="false"
link="http://triptych.brynmawr.edu/u?/HC_QuakSlav,9674">
Moses Brown, Providence RI, had a vision that God required him to liberate his slaves. He did so and became a Quaker.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1774 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="New York Yearly Meeting forbids slaveholding"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
New York Yearly Meeting forbids slaveholding  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1774 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Philadelphia Yearly Meeting disowns Friends for buying and selling slaves"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Philadelphia Yearly Meeting made slave buying, selling disownable offenses. Slave owners were to be confronted by their meetings and removed from leadership positions.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1774 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="New Jersey Friends draft public petition for emancipation"
 isDuration="false"
link="http://triptych.brynmawr.edu/u?/HC_QuakSlav,10005">
Quakers in New Jersey got up a public petition signed by 3,000 people advocating emancipation for all the slaves in the province.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1775 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="First abolitionist society is formed"
 isDuration="false"
link="http://triptych.brynmawr.edu/u?/HC_QuakSlav,444">
The Society for the Relief of Free Negroes Unlawfully held in bondage, later to become the Pennsylvania Abolition Society, is established in Philadelphia with a largely Quaker membership.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1776 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Declaration of Independence"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
"We hold these truths to be self-evident, that all men are created equal, that they are endowed by their Creator with certain unalienable Rights, that among these are Life, Liberty and the pursuit of Happiness"  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1776 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Philadelphia Yearly Meeting prohibits slaveholding"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Philadelphia Yearly Meeting prohibited slave ownership among its members  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1778 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Pennsylvania Quakers form committees to aid their ex-slaves"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Philadelphia Yearly Meeting urged local meetings to appoint committees to look after the temporal and spiritual welfare of their former slaves.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1778 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Baltimore Yearly Meeting disowns slaveholders"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Maryland Yearly Meeting disowned slaveholders and prohibited members from hiring slaves or serving as overseers of slaves on the plantations of others.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1780 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Emancipation in Pennsylvania"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Pennsylvania passes an Emancipation Act which frees people born in 1780 and after, though those freed people remain "servants" until the age of 28.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1781 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="North Carolina Yearly Meeting disowns slaveholding Friends"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
North Carolina Yearly Meeting decreed expulsion for Friends who were unwilling to free their slaves.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1782 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="New England Yearly Meeting reports no members have slaves"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
New England Yearly Meeting wrote to London Yearly Meeting that all members were clear of holding or dealing with slavery.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1783 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="London Friends petition British government to abolish slave trade"
 isDuration="false"
link="http://triptych.brynmawr.edu/u?/HC_QuakSlav,9654">
Benezet to London Friends urging them to renew the fight against the slave trade. London Yearly Meeting resolved to approach the House with a petition signed by 258 Quakers asking for abolition of slave traffic in all British Colonies.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1783 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Philadelphia Friends petition Congress against the slave trade"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Philadelphia Yearly Meeting drew up a petition against the slave trade which 535 members signed and presented it to Congress.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1784 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Virginia Yearly Meeting disowns slaveholders"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Virginia Yearly Meeting decreed a categorical prohibition on slave-owning.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1784 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Gradual emancipation in Rhode Island"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Rhode Island assessed a manumission law that also stated that all Negroes born in the state after March of that year should be free. In October the state forbade its citizens further participation in the slave trade.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1785 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Negro Committee of Philadelphia Yearly Meeting addresses Congress"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
The "Negro Committee" of Philadelphia Yearly Meeting tries to convince the Confederation Congress to prohibit slavery  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1785 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="New York bans importation of slaves"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
New York banned the importation of slaves after a petition presented by the Quakers.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1785 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="New York Manumission Society"
 isDuration="false"
link="http://triptych.brynmawr.edu/u?/HC_QuakSlav,4632">
The New York Manumission Society is established by John Jay, Alexander Hamilton, and Quakers.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1786 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Quakers urge national government to prohibit slavery"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Philadelphia and New York Yearly Meetings try to persuade the government to prohibit slavery.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1786 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="George Washington criticizes the Pennsylvania Abolition Society"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
In a letter of April 12, 1786, Washington complains about "a society of Quakers" recently formed in Pennsylvania that would hinder rather than assist attempts to recover fugitive slaves.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1787 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Isaac Hopper moves to Philadelphia"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Isaac Hopper is often credited as being the "Father of the Underground Railroad." It is estimated that he began assisting slaves to freedom in the late 1790s.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1787 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="New York Yearly Meeting reports no member have slaves"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
New York Yearly Meeting reports that no member holds slaves.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1787 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Pennsylvania Society for Promoting the Abolition of Slavery"
 isDuration="false"
link="http://triptych.brynmawr.edu/u?/HC_QuakSlav,1046">
Pennsylvania Society for Promoting the Abolition of Slavery and the Relief of Free Negroes Unlawfully Held in Bondage and for Improving the Condition of the African Race, originally formed in 1775 as the Society for the Relief of Free Negroes held in Bondage, is incorportaed with an explicitly anti-slavery focus and with the involvement of non-Quakers including Benjamin Rush and Benjamin Franklin.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1787 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="United States Constitution is ratified"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
The United States Constitution as adopted in 1787 includes clauses recognizing the existence of slavery including a provision for the return of "fugitives from labor" (Article IV, Section 2), a provision not to prohibit the importation of slaves until 1808 (Article 1, Section 9), and a provision to enumerate slaves as three-fifths of a person (Article 1, Section 2).  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1789 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Delaware bans importation of slaves"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
The state of Delaware passed a bill prohibiting foreign slave trade and decreed that slaves resident in the state could not be sold South without a license.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1789 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Quakers urge national government to prohibit slavery"
 isDuration="false"
link="http://triptych.brynmawr.edu/u?/HC_QuakSlav,3702">
Philadelphia and New York Yearly Meetings approached Congress to "remedy against the gross national iniquity of trafficking in the persons of fellow men." Senators and representatives were interviewed and the appeal was referred to the committee of the House. This request sparked impassioned debates in Congress that lasted for months. The memorandum prepared by the committee reviewed the constitutional limitations on the powers of Congress, asserted Congress' rights to levy a ten dollar duty on slaves and to require the humane treatment of slaves carried on vessels of American registry, and its power to prevent the supplying of slaves for foreign markets by Americans, or foreigners from fitting out slave ships in American ports. Eventually the report was accepted but watered down to a mere statement of the constitutional limitations on its powers in regard to slavery, and an assertion of the right to regulate the slave trade to foreign ports.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1793 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="’A Serious Expostulation’"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Warner Mifflin  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1793 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="First Fugitive Slave Law"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Congress enacted the Fugitive Slave Law.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1794 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="American Convention of Abolition Societies"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
First meeting of the American Convention of Abolition Societies. Meetings are held from 1794 to 1829, usually in Philadelphia.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1796 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Philadelphia Yearly Meeting opens membership to blacks"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Philadelphia Yearly Meeting agreed to entertain application for membership without distinction of color.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1797 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Philadelphia Quakers address antislavery memorial to Congress"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Philadelphia Yearly Meeting drew up a memorial to Congress concerning slaves and requesting action. This, again, touched on the differences of opinions within the Congress, both on slavery and about Quakers. Congress responded to the Quaker petition of 1797 in that the matter seemed to be one which the courts, not Congress, should decide, and returned the petition to the Philadelphia Friends.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1799 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Gradual emancipation in New York"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
The New York legislature passed a gradual emancipation act upon pressure from the New York Yearly Meeting and Manumission Society.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1799 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Philadelphia Yearly Meeting publishes ‘To our fellow citizens’"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Philadelphia Yearly Meeting published To our fellow citizens of the United States of North America : and others who it may concern. "When people begin to write the history of their great deeds of the past, the moment often marks the end of their heroic period."  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1803 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Louisiana Purchase"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1806 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="’Remarks on the slavery of the black people’"
 isDuration="false"
link="http://triptych.brynmawr.edu/u?/HC_QuakSlav,7975">
John Parrish, (1729-1807), published Remarks on the slavery of the black people : addressed to the citizens of the United States, urging Americans to consider abolition of slavery, not just the slave trade.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1807 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="United States bans the importation of slaves"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Congress enacted a bill prohibiting the importation of slaves to take effect on 1/1/1808  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1807 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Slave Trade Act halts slave importation to all British colonies"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Great Britain enacted a bill prohibiting the importation of slaves.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1808 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="North Carolina Yearly Meeting protects freedmen"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
North Carolina Yearly Meeting appointed trustees to hold nominal titles to emancipated Africans. This move was to circumvent North Carolina law which allowed freed slaves to be seized and resold into slavery.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1811 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="’Observations on the Slavery of the Africans and their descendents’"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Elias Hicks, encouraging Friends not to use goods created by slave labor, published , Observations on the slavery of the Africans and their descendants: Recommended to…the citizens of the United States. It circulated primarily among Friends. Hicks' notoriety on theological matters confused Friends on the "right" stance concerning Free Produce .  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1816 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="American Colonization Society"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
American Colonization Society is founded with the goal of resettling freed slaves in Africa.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1816 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Cuffe brings first African American colonists to Sierra Leone"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Paul Cuffe was admitted into membership with Friends at Acoaxet, MA in 1808. In 1811, Paul Cuffee visited Sierra Leone to evaluate conditions for colonization established African Societies among Negroes in New York and Philadelphia and distributed descriptions of Sierra Leone.  Cuffe captained a ship of African American colonists to Sierra Leone in 1815-1816.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1817 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="’The Philanthropist' begins publication"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Charles Osborn, farmer and Quaker minister, publishes Philanthropist (1817-18), sometimes called the first abolitionist paper in America.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1819 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="’The Emancipator’ begins publication"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Elihu Embree, a Tennessee iron manufacturer, and member of the Tennessee Society for Promoting the Manumission of Slaves, publishes Manumission Intelligencer, afterward the Emancipator (1819-20) of Jonesboro, Tennessee. It was the first entirely abolitionist organ in the country.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1820 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Missouri Compromise"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1821 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="’Genius of Universal Emancipation’"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Benjamin Lundy publishes Genius of Universal Emancipation (1821-39) begun in Mount Pleasant, Ohio.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1824 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Elizabeth Heyrick publishes ‘Immediate, not gradual abolition’"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
British Friend Elizabeth Coltman Heyrick publishes Immediate, not gradual abolition : or, An inquiry into the shortest, safest, and most effectual means of getting rid of West Indian slavery,  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1826 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="First free-produce store opens in Baltimore"
 isDuration="false"
link="http://triptych.brynmawr.edu/u?/HC_QuakSlav,4633">
Beginning in 1826, a number of organizations are established to advocate the non-use of the products of slave labor, and to promote the manufacture and sale of "free produce" cloth, sugar and other goods. Most of the support for free produce somes from Quakers. Benjamin Lundy, Quaker antislavery editor, opened a free-produce store in Baltimore and the Free Produce Society of Pennsylvania is formed.  He was a sadler and organized the first abolition society in Ohio, the Union Humane Society.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1827 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="’The African Observer’"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Enoch Lewis publishes African Observer (1827-28) in Philadelphia.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1827 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="The Pennsylvania Free Produce Association is founded"
 isDuration="false"
link="http://triptych.brynmawr.edu/u?/HC_QuakSlav,4633">
The Pennsylvania Free Produce Association is founded.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1827 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Hicksite-Orthodox Separation"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
In 1827-1828, the Hicksite-Orthodox separation divides Philadelphia, New York, Ohio and Indiana Yearly Meetings. New England, North Carolina and London Yearly Meeting side with the Orthodox Friends.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1831 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="’The Liberator’"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Garrison, writing against gradual change, founded The Liberator and marks the end of Quaker leadership in the cause of abolition. He had previously worked with Benjamin Lundy on the "Genius of Universal Emancipation"  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1831 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Friends fruitlessly petition Ohio and Indiana legislatures"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Friends fruitlessly petitioned both the Ohio and Indiana legislatures for repeal of discriminatory laws like the Black Code.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1832 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="New England antislavery Society is founded"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Arnold Buffum, Quaker, became the first president of the Massachusetts (or New England) Anti-Slavery Society, organized by Garrison in Boston.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1833 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Great Britain passes Slavery Abolition Act"
 isDuration="false"
link="http://triptych.brynmawr.edu/u?/HC_QuakSlav,2489">
The act abolishes slavery in the British Empire effective August 1, 1834, though an "apprenticeship" system is in place until 1838.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1833 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Prudence Crandall admits a mixed-race child to her school"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Prudence Crandall, Quaker schoolmistress in Canterbury Connecticut, admitted a mulatto child into the school. Criticism of this act led her to fill the school with solely Negro girls. The Liberator defended her against prosecution.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1833 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="American Anti-Slavery Society"
 isDuration="false"
link="http://triptych.brynmawr.edu/u?/HC_QuakSlav,8637">
A National Antislavery Convention was held in Philadelphia presided by Evan Lewis, Quaker. Garrison had suggested that the Pennsylvania Abolition Society sponsor this convention to connect the more radical abolitionists with the older, respectable abolition movement, long centered in Philadelphia. The convention founded the American Anti-Slavery Society with a platform of immediate, unconditional emancipation. By 1836, The American Anti-Slavery Society had established 500 local societies in the North  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1833 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Philadelphia Female Anti-Slavery Society"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1834 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="London Yearly Meeting opposes Colonization"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
London Yearly Meeting urged Orthodox American Friends to work for emancipation in America, not colonization in Liberia  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1835 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Quakers unsuccessfully petition Congress for emancipation"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Lindley Coates and Caln Quarterly Meeting (Hicksite) petitioned the federal government to free slaves in the constitutional jurisdiction of Congress causing the anti-slavery question to be foremost in Congress. The petition was received but rejected.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1836 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Indiana Quakers oppose colonization"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Indiana Yearly Meeting took a stand against colonization and discouraged its members from going outside the Society of Friends in their antislavery work.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1837 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Orthodox Friends publish antislavery pamphlets"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Orthodox Friends in New York, Philadelphia, New England and Indiana publish anti-slavery pamphlets, cautiously urging Americans to recognize slavery for the evil that it was, and to take steps looking toward its eradication.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1837 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Association of Friends for Promoting the Abolition of Slavery"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Association of Friends for Promoting the Abolition of Slavery and Improving the Conditions of Philadelphia, a largely Hicksite organization, is established in Philadelphia.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1838 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Requited Labor Convention"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
The Requited Labor Convention is held in Philadelphia, May 1838; in 1839, the organization is renamed the American Free Produce Association.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1838 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Pennsylvania Hall"
 isDuration="false"
link="http://triptych.brynmawr.edu/u?/HC_QuakSlav,9589">
Pennsylvania Hall (6th and Haines, Philadelphia) is built and burned. Erected to house the offices of the Pennsylvania State Anti-Slavery Society and provide a space for lectures. It was destroyed by a mob after three days of dedication and reformists' meetings. Tensions tightened between the position of quiest Friends and ardent Quaker reformers.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1839 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Hicksite Friends work in antislavery movement"
 isDuration="false"
link="http://triptych.brynmawr.edu/u?/HC_QuakSlav,7164">
Baltimore Hicksite Yearly Meeting pointed out the necessity of testing Friends' antislavery activities in the light of their testimony against war and of "all those passions in ourselves or others which lead to contention and violence." Philadelphia Hicksites issued three addresses to their members to work for abolition. Isaac Hopper, Charles Marriott, and James Gibbons, New York Hicksite Friends, organized the New York Association of Friends for the Relief of Those Held in Slavery.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1840 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Controversy among Friends over goals and tactics of antislavery movement"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1840 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="World Anti-Slavery Convention"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Held in London  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1840 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="American Antislavery Society splits"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
In 1840, The American Anti-Slavery Society had 2,000 local societies in the North with a membership from 150,000 to 200,000. It split over the issue of women's membership.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1840 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Hicksite Friends in Philadelphia found Quaker antislavery group"
 isDuration="false"
link="http://triptych.brynmawr.edu/u?/HC_QuakSlav,1047">
Philadelphia Hicksite Quakers founded the Association for Promoting the Abolition of Slavery, initially known as "Association of Friends for Advocating the Cause of the Slave, and Improving the Condition of Free People of Color, after the Yearly Meeting refused to take corporate action but encouraged members to do so.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1841 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Philadelphia Quakers publish materials incriminating domestic slave trade"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Philadelphia Hicksite Quakers published an exposé of the domestic slave trade and Philadelphia Orthodox Quakers published an account of the illegal participation of American citizens in the African trade.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1841 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Indiana Friends establish abolitionist newspapers"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Arnold Buffum, disowned Quaker from the east, settled in Indiana and started a newspaper, The Protectionist (January 8 – December 16, 1841), sponsored by the Indiana State Anti-Slavery Society. Also in 1841, Indiana Friends organized a Friends' Anti-Slavery Society and started a newspaper, Free Labor Advocate and Anti-Slavery Chronicle.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1841 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Indiana Quakers close meetinghouses to abolitionist lecturers"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Indiana Yearly Meeting closes its meetinghouses to antislavery lecturers.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1842 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Hicksite Friends in Baltimore advocate antislavery by example"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
The Baltimore Yearly Meeting (Hicksite) issued a paper urging members to be "quiet, and mind our own business", live a "testimony of example" and not become involved with the anti-slavery issues. Many Quaker abolitionists were incensed and Quaker pro-abolition activities were encouraged.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1842 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="New England Quakers publish an appeal to slaveholders"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
New England Yearly Meeting published an appeal to southern Christians which was also circulated by meetings in New York and Indiana.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1842 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Isaac Hopper, Charles Marriott, James Gibbons disowned"
 isDuration="false"
link="http://triptych.brynmawr.edu/u?/HC_QuakSlav,7465">
Isaac Hopper, Charles Marriott and James Gibbons were disowned from New York Monthly, Quarterly and Yearly Meetings for publishing an incendiary anti-slavery article critical of Friends that excited discord and disunity.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1842 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Indiana Yearly Meeting removes radical abolitionists from leadership"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Indiana Yearly Meeting decreed that those not in accord with Friends' stance on antislavery reform should not be permitted to serve on important committees.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1843 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="’A Brief Statement of the Rise and Progress’"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Orthodox Philadelphian Friends published the story of the Quaker anti-slavery crusade of colonial and early national times, "A Brief Statement of the Rise and Progress", and reaffirmed the validity of the temperate approach to the abolition of slavery.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1843 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Indiana Yearly Meeting of Antislavery Friends opens"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Indiana Friends who had been removed from leadership positions organized the "Indiana Yearly Meeting of Anti-Slavery Friends". Five quarterly meetings, twelve monthly meetings and 2,000 members of 25,000 Orthodox Friends left the parent body.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1843 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="North Carolina Yearly Meeting adopts minute against assisting fugitive slaves"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
North Carolina Friends adopted a minute against giving shelter improperly to runaway slaves to refute accusations that they supported the Underground Railroad.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1845 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Free Produce Associations formed in New York and Philadelphia"
 isDuration="false"
link="http://triptych.brynmawr.edu/u?/HC_QuakSlav,494">
Free Produce Association of Friends of New York Yearly Meeting and the Free Produce Association of Friends of Philadelphia Yearly Meeting, are established.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1847 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="’The Friends Review’"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
The Friends Review was started by the evangelical-minded members of Philadelphia Yearly Meeting. Enoch Lewis was the editor.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1848 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="’The Non-Slaveholder’"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
The Non-Slaveholder, a periodical advocating free produce and edited by Abraham Pennock, Samuel Rhodes and George Truman begins publication in Philadelphia.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1850 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Fugitive Slave Law of 1850"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Conservative American Quakers felt obliged to discourage members from violent opposition to the hateful Fugitive Slave Law.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1851 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Christiana Resistance"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
An attempt to recapture fugitive slaves near Christiana, Pennsylvania, on September 11, 1851, is met with armed resistance by African-Americans resulting in the death of the slave owner. Quakers are among those arrested.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1852 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="’Uncle Tom's Cabin’"
 isDuration="false"
link="http://triptych.brynmawr.edu/u?/HC_QuakSlav,8562">
Harriet Beecher Stowe's "Uncle Tom's Cabin" published. It has a major impact on arousing anti-slavery feeling in the north. Quakers are portrayed as actively involved in the Underground Railroad.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1853 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Pennsylvania Yearly Meeting of Progressive Friends"
 isDuration="false"
link="http://triptych.brynmawr.edu/u?/HC_QuakSlav,1069">
Radical Quakers in Chester County, Pennsylvania, and elsewhere organize the Yearly Meeting of Progressive Friends to promote anti-slavery and other reforms. Annual meteings are held at Longwood until 1940.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1853 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="British Friends deliver antislavery address to US Government"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
British Friends send a delegation to the US Government to deliver an antislavery address from London Yearly Meeting.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1854 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Kansas-Nebraska Act"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
The Kansas-Nebraska bill is passed, repealing the Missouri Compromise. It contained a "popular sovereignty" provision that allowed settlers to vote on whether the new territories would be slave or free states.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1859 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="John Brown's Raid on Harpers Ferry"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
Edwin and Barclay Coppoc, Iowa Quakers, participate with John Brown to free the Virginia slaves. Edwin was hanged with Brown.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1861 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Civil War begins"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
While the meetings in the northern states maintained their traditional pacifist position, a significant number of young men join the Union army. In contrast, Quakers in the southern states reject any military service with the Confederate army. Quakers during and after the Civil War organize associations for the care and education of the newly freed people in the south.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1863 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="Emancipation Proclamation"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
The Emancipation Proclamation, effective January 1, 1863, frees enslaved peoples in the Confederacy.  </event>
  <event start=" Jan 01 1865 00:00:00 GMT " 
title="13th Amendment"
 isDuration="false"
link="">
The 13th Amendment to the United States Constitution abolishes slavery throughout the United States.  </event>


 </data>